<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Reserach on Gauti B. Eggertsson</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reserach on Gauti B. Eggertsson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.136.5</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recent and Forthcoming Reserach</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/recent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/recent/</guid>
      <description>This section contains most recent and forthcoming work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Slanted-L Phillips Curve</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper3/</guid>
      <description>A slanted-L curve is well-suited to represent the non-linearity of the celebrated Phillips curve. We show this using cross-country data of major industrialized economies since 2009, including the inflationary surge of the 2020s. At high unemployment rates, an increase in demand reduces unemployment without creating strong inflationary pressures. Meanwhile, supply shocks have a muted effect. At sufficiently low unemployment, there is a labor shortage, so that the economy is at full capacity. Then, higher demand is inflationary, and supply shocks are amplified. We derive a model of a slanted-L curve.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It’s Baaack: The Inflation Surge of 2020s and the Return of the Non-Linear Phillips Curve</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper1/</guid>
      <description>This paper proposes a non-linear New Keynesian Phillips curve (Inv-L NK Phillips Curve) to explain the surge of inflation in the 2020s. Economic slack is measured as firms&amp;#39; job vacancies over the number of unemployed workers. After showing empirical evidence of statistically significant nonlinearities, we propose a New Keynesian model with search and matching frictions, complemented by a form of wage rigidity, in the spirit of Phillips (1958), that generates strong nonlinearities. Policy implications include the thesis that appropriate monetary policy can bring inflation down without a significant recession and that the recent inflationary surge was mostly generated by a labor shortage -- i.e. an exceptionally tight labor market.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Inflation Surge of the 2020: The Role of Monetary Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hugo-website/papers/paper2/</guid>
      <description>Gauti Eggertsson of Brown University and Don Kohn of the Hutchins Center at Brookings (and a former vice chair of the Federal Reserve Board) conclude that the Fed’s substantial revisions to its monetary policy strategy in August 2020 and its forward guidance contributed to the largely unanticipated and most definitely unwelcome surge in inflation during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
