<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Reserach on Gauti B. Eggertsson</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reserach on Gauti B. Eggertsson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.136.5</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Theory of the Great Depression and the Great Recession</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-unified-theory-of-the-great-depression-and-the-great-recession/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-unified-theory-of-the-great-depression-and-the-great-recession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Eggertsson_JEL.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a unified framework to explain three major economic downturns: the U.S.
Great Depression, the U.S. Great Recession, and Japan’s Long Recession. Temporary economic
disruptions,such as banking crises and excessive debt accumulation, can drive natural interest rates
into negative territory in the short term. At the same time, structural factors, including
demographic decline and rising inequality, can depress natural interest rates over short and long
horizons. A negative natural interest rate and the zero lower bound (ZLB) are necessary
conditions for a liquidity trap. Credible monetary policy can counteract the adverse effects of
short-run liquidity traps. Diminished monetary policy credibility or persistent negative natural
rates may necessitate fiscal interventions. The framework sheds light on the macroeconomic
challenges of low-interest-rate environments and underscores the central importance of
policy regimes. We close by reflecting on the great macroeconomic question of our time: Will
short-term interest rates collapse back to zero once the inflation surge of the 2020s moves to the
back mirror and the political landscape in the US has dramatically changed?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Forward Guidence Puzzle is not a Puzzle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-forward-guidence-puzzle-is-not-a-puzzle/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-forward-guidence-puzzle-is-not-a-puzzle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Eggertsson_Schuele_FGP.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standard New Keynesian models, future interest rate cuts have larger effects than current cuts—this is called the forward guidance puzzle. We argue that the forward guidance puzzle is not a puzzle. We show the puzzle arises from an implausibly large monetary regime change, exceeding anything in U.S. history since the Great Depression. By calibrating our model to four regime changes during the U.S. Great Depression, disciplined by changes in long-term bond yields, we find the model’s predictions are broadly consistent with historical data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Slanted-L Phillips Curve</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-slanted-l-phillips-curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-slanted-l-phillips-curve/</guid>
      <description>A slanted-L curve effectively captures the non-linearity of the Phillips curve, as shown using cross-country data from major industrialized economies since 2009. The model demonstrates that at high unemployment, demand increases have limited inflationary effects, while at low unemployment, labor shortages amplify both inflationary pressures and the impact of supply shocks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It’s Baaack: The Inflation Surge of 2020s and the Return of the Non-Linear Phillips Curve</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/its-baaack_the-inflation-surge-of-2020s-and-the-return-of-the-non-linear-phillips-curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/its-baaack_the-inflation-surge-of-2020s-and-the-return-of-the-non-linear-phillips-curve/</guid>
      <description>This paper introduces a non-linear New Keynesian Phillips curve (Inv-L NK Phillips Curve) to explain the inflation surge in the 2020s, using job vacancies relative to unemployed workers as a measure of economic slack. It argues that wage rigidity and labor market frictions create strong nonlinearities, suggesting that inflation can be reduced without a severe recession, with the recent surge largely driven by a labor shortage.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative Nominal Interest Rates and the Bank Lending Channel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/negative-nominal-interest-rates-and-the-bank-lending-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/negative-nominal-interest-rates-and-the-bank-lending-channel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Negative_interest_rates_and_the_bank_lending_channel__Revised.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nber.org/papers/w25416&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NBER&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We investigate the bank lending channel of negative nominal policy rates from an empirical and theoretical perspective. We ﬁnd that retail household deposit rates are subject to a lower bound (DLB). Empirically, once the DLB is met, the pass-through to lending rates and credit volumes is substantially lower and bank equity values decline in response to further policy rate cuts. We construct a banking sector model and use our estimate of the pass-through of negative policy rates to lending rates as an identiﬁed moment to parameterize the model and assess the impact of negative policy rates in general equilibrium. Using the theoretical framework, we derive a suﬃcient statistic for when negative policy rates are expansionary and when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Inflation Surge of the 2020: The Role of Monetary Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-inflation-surge-of-the-2020-the-role-of-monetary-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-inflation-surge-of-the-2020-the-role-of-monetary-policy/</guid>
      <description>The Fed’s substantial revisions to its monetary policy strategy in August 2020 and its forward guidance contributed to the largely unanticipated and most definitely unwelcome surge in inflation during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Consistency and the Duration of Government Debt: A Model of Quantitative Easing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/time-consistency-and-the-duration-of-government-debt-a-model-of-quantitative-easing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/time-consistency-and-the-duration-of-government-debt-a-model-of-quantitative-easing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;QEPaper_Final_Revision_2022.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a model of quantitative easing (QE) at the zero lower bound
(ZLB) on the short-term nominal interest rate. QE, which reduces the maturity of
government debt, is effective at the ZLB because it generates expectations of future
monetary expansion in a time-consistent equilibrium. Numerical experiments show that
this effect can be substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-BibTeX&#34; data-lang=&#34;BibTeX&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;related-material&#34;&gt;Related material&lt;/h5&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mr. Keynes and the Classics; A Suggested Reinterpretation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/mr-keynes-and-the-classics-a-suggested-reinterpretation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/mr-keynes-and-the-classics-a-suggested-reinterpretation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Keynes_Classics_NBER.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper revisits and proposes a resolution to an empirical and theoretical controversy between Keynes and the “classics” (or monetarists). The controversy dates to Keynes’s General Theory (1936)—most famously formalized in Hicks’s (1937) classic Econometrica article, in which the IS-LM model is first formally stated. We first replicate empirical tests formulated in the late 1960s and ’70s and show that more recent data have more statistical power and resolve the empirical debate in favor of the Keynesians, at least according to the criteria of the literature at that time. We then show, using a simple dynamic stochastic general equilibrium (DSGE) model, that the empirical tests suffer from the Lucas (1976) critique, as the conclusion fundamentally depends upon the assumed policy regime. Nevertheless, we argue, this new empirical result is useful: it provides evidence for the existence of a “Keynesian policy regime” according to which traditional monetary expansion loses its impact in the absence of a policy regime change, in the sense of Sargent (1982).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Medium-Term Money Neutrality and the Effective Lower Bound</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/medium-term-money-neutrality-and-the-effective-lower-bound/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/medium-term-money-neutrality-and-the-effective-lower-bound/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;w27669.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional wisdom suggests that medium-term money neutrality imposes strong limitations on
the effects of monetary policy. The point of this paper is that models with medium- and long-term
money  neutrality  are  prone  to  generate  non-existence  of  equilibria  at  the  effective  lower  bound
(ELB) on  interest  rates.  Non-existence  is  suggestive  of  sharp  output  contractions  &amp;mdash;  so-called
contractionary  black  holes  &amp;mdash;  at  the  ELB.  Paradoxically,  the  case  for  expansionary  monetary
policy  at  the  ELB  is  even  stronger  in  models  that  feature  near  money  neutrality.  The  results
highlight  the  benefits  of  a  monetary  policy  regime  in  which  the  central  bank  temporarily
overshoots its inflation target once confronted by the ELB.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log-linear Approximation versus an Exact Solution at the ZLB in the New Keynesian Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/log-linear-approximation-versus-an-exact-solution-at-the-zlb-in-the-new-keynesian-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/log-linear-approximation-versus-an-exact-solution-at-the-zlb-in-the-new-keynesian-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/22784.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;LogLin.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How accurate is a log-linear approximation of the New Keynesian model when the nominal interest rate is bounded by zero? This paper compares the solution of the exact non-linear model to the log-linear approximation. It finds that the difference is modest. This applies even for extreme events in numerical experiments that replicate the U.S. Great Depression. The exact non-linear model makes the same predictions as the log-linear approximation for key policy questions such as the size and sign of government spending and tax multipliers. It also replicates well known paradoxes like the paradox of toil and the paradox of price flexibility. The paper also reconciles different findings reported in the literature using Calvo versus Rotemberg pricing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Debt Deleveraging and Optimal Monetary Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/dynamic-debt-deleveraging-and-optimal-monetary-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/dynamic-debt-deleveraging-and-optimal-monetary-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;OMPD-FINALE-250119.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper proposes a post-crisis New Keynesian model that incorporates agent heterogeneity in borrowing and lending with a minimum set of assumptions and complexity. Unlike the standard framework, this model makes the natural rate of interest endogenous, and dependent on macroeconomic policy. We establish microfoundations
for debt deleveraging based both on the accumulation of excessive debt by households and leverage constraints on banks, showing that they are isomorphic and thus integrating two popular narratives for the crisis of 2008. The main application is to study optimal monetary policy at the zero lower bound (ZLB). Such policy succeeds in raising the natural rate of interest by creating an environment that speeds up deleveraging and thus endogenously shortens the crisis and the duration of binding ZLB. Inflation should be front-loaded and overshoot its long term target during the ZLB episode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Toolkit for Solving Models with a Lower Bound on Interest Rates of Stochastic Duration</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-toolkit-for-solving-models-with-a-lower-bound-on-interest-rates-of-stochastic-duration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-toolkit-for-solving-models-with-a-lower-bound-on-interest-rates-of-stochastic-duration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;ZLB_Toolkit.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The macroeconomic data of the last thirty years has overturned at least two of Kaldor’s famous stylized growth facts: constant interest rates, and a constant labor share. At the same time, the research of Piketty and others has introduced several new and surprising facts: an increase in the financial wealth-to-output ratio in the US, an increase in measured Tobin’s Q, and a divergence between the marginal and the average return on capital. In this paper, we argue that these trends can be explained by an increase in market power and pure profits in the US economy, i.e., the emergence of a non-zero-rent economy, along with forces that have led to a persistent long term decline in real interest rates. We make three parsimonious modifications to the standard neoclassical model to explain these trends. Using recent estimates of the increase in markups and the decrease in real interest rates, we show that our model can quantitatively match these new stylized macroeconomic facts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kaldor and Piketty’s Facts: The Rise of Monopoly Power in the United States</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/kaldors-and-pikettys-facts-the-rise-of-monopoly-power-in-the-united-states/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/kaldors-and-pikettys-facts-the-rise-of-monopoly-power-in-the-united-states/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Kaldor_project_JME.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nber.org/papers/w24287&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NBER&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The macroeconomic data of the last fifty years have overturned at least two of Kaldor’s famous stylized
growth facts: constant interest rates, and a constant labor share. At the same time, the research of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piketty and others has introduced several new and surprising facts: an increase in the financial wealth-
to-output ratio in the US, an increase in measured Tobin’s Q, and a divergence between the marginal and&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Contagious Malady? Open Economy Dimensions of Secular Stagnation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-contagious-malady-open-economy-dimensions-of-secular-stagnation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-contagious-malady-open-economy-dimensions-of-secular-stagnation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/pal/imfecr/v64y2016i4d10.1057_s41308-016-0019-8.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;EMSS.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions of secular stagnation—low interest rates, below target inflation, and sluggish output growth—characterize much of the global economy. We consider an overlapping generations, open economy model of secular stagnation, and examine the effect of capital flows on the transmission of stagnation. In a world with a low natural rate of interest, greater capital integration transmits recessions across countries as opposed to lower interest rates. In a global secular stagnation, expansionary fiscal policy carries positive spillovers implying gains from coordination, and fiscal policy is self-financing. Expansionary monetary policy, by contrast, is beggar-thy-neighbor with output gains in one country coming at the expense of the other. Similarly, we find that competitiveness policies including structural labor market reforms or neomercantilist trade policies are also beggar-thy-neighbor in a global secular stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bernanke’s No-Arbitrage Argument Revisited: Can Open Market Operations in Real Assets Eliminate the Liquidity Trap?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/bernankes-no-arbitrage-argument-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/bernankes-no-arbitrage-argument-revisited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/22243.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;ChileEggProuxl.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first show that, at least in theory, open market operations in real assets can be a useful tool for overcoming a liquidity trap because they change the inflation incentives of the government, and thus change private sector expectations from deflationary to inflationary. We argue that this formalizes Ben Bernanke&amp;rsquo;s arbitrage argument for why a central bank can always increase nominal demand, despite the zero lower bound. We illustrate this logic in a calibrated New Keynesian model assuming the government acts under discretion. Numerical experiments suggest, however, that the needed intervention is incredibly high, creating a serious limitation of this solution to the liquidity trap. Our experiments suggest that while asset purchases can be a helpful commitment device in theory, they may need to be combined in practice with fiscal policy coordination to achieve the desired outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secular Stagnation in the Open Economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/secular-stagnation-in-the-open-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/secular-stagnation-in-the-open-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v106y2016i5p503-07.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;AER-P&amp;amp;PEggMehrSumm.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conditions of secular stagnation&amp;ndash;low interest rates, below target inflation, and sluggish output growth&amp;ndash;now characterize much of the global economy. We consider a simple two-country textbook model to examine how capital markets transmit secular stagnation and to study policy externalities across countries. We find capital flows transmit recessions in a world with low interest rates and that policies that attempt to boost national saving are beggar-thy-neighbor. Monetary expansion cannot eliminate a secular stagnation and may have beggar-thy-neighbor effects, while sufficiently large fiscal interventions can eliminate a secular stagnation and carry positive externalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can structural reforms help Europe?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/can-structural-reforms-help-europe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/can-structural-reforms-help-europe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/moneco/v61y2014icp2-22.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;JME.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structural reforms that increase competition in product and labor markets are often indicated as the main policy option available for peripheral Europe to regain competitiveness and boost output. We show that, in a crisis that pushes the nominal interest rate to its lower bound, these reforms do not support economic activity in the short run, and may well be contractionary. In the absence of the appropriate monetary stimulus, reforms fuel expectations of prolonged deflation, increase the real interest rate, and depress aggregate demand. Our findings carry important implications for the current debate on the timing and the design of structural reforms in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deficits, Public Debt Dynamics and Tax and Spending Multipliers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/deficits-public-debt-dynamics-and-tax-and-spending-multipliers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/deficits-public-debt-dynamics-and-tax-and-spending-multipliers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ecj/econjl/vy2013ip133-163.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;EJ.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cutting government spending on goods and services increases the budget deficit if the nominal interest rate is close to zero. This is the message of a simple but standard New Keynesian DSGE model calibrated with Bayesian methods. The cut in spending reduces output and thus?holding rates for labor and sales taxes constant?reduces revenues by even more than what is saved by the spending cut. Similarly, increasing sales taxes can increase the budget deficit rather than reduce it. Both results suggest limitations of ?austerity measures? in low interest rate economies to cut budget deficits. Running budget deficits can by itself be either expansionary or contractionary for output, depending on how deficits interact with expectations about the long run in the model. If deficits trigger expectations of i) lower long-run government spending, ii) higher long-run sales taxes, or iii) higher future inflation, they are expansionary. If deficits trigger expectations of higher long-run labor taxes or lower long-run productivity, they are contractionary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fiscal Multipliers and Policy Coordination</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/fiscal-multipliers-and-policy-coordination/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/fiscal-multipliers-and-policy-coordination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/h/chb/bcchsb/v17c06pp175-234.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;EggertssonChile.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper analyzes the effectiveness of fiscal policy at zero nominal interest rates. I solve a stochastic general equilibrium model with sticky prices assuming that the government cannot commit to future policy. Real government spending increases demand by boosting public consumption. Deficit spending increases demand by generating inflation expectations. I compute multipliers of government spending that calculate by how much each dollar of spending increases output. Both the deficit and the real spending multipliers can be large, but the multiplier of deficit spending depends critically on monetary and fiscal cooperation: it can be large with cooperation and zero without it. The theory suggests one interesting interpretation of why recovery measures–such as fiscal spending, exchange interventions, and large increases in the money supply–had a smaller effect on nominal demand in Japan during the Great Recession (1992-2006) than during the US&amp;rsquo;s Great Depression (1929-1941). In both episodes, the short-term nominal interest rate was close to zero. The theory suggests that part of the difference can be explained by the fact that, while monetary and fiscal policy were coordinated in the US during the Great Depression, they were not in Japan during the Great Recession. The overall conclusion of the paper is that the effect of given policy actions depends crucially on the institutional setup in the economy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debt, Deleveraging, and the Liquidity Trap: A Fisher-Minsky-Koo Approach</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/debt-deleveraging-and-the-liquidity-trap-a-fisher-minsky-koo-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/debt-deleveraging-and-the-liquidity-trap-a-fisher-minsky-koo-approach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/oup/qjecon/v127y2012i3p1469-1513.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Eggertsson_Krugman_2012.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BxVZWdXdGQH8azYxckkzSEUwMWc/view?resourcekey=0-jhNM4bVjb5tVDHdIaoEbRg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Web Appendix&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article we present a simple new Keynesian&amp;ndash;style model of debt-driven slumps&amp;ndash;that is, situations in which an overhang of debt on the part of some agents, who are forced into rapid deleveraging, is depressing aggregate demand. Making some agents debt-constrained is a surprisingly powerful assumption. Fisherian debt deflation, the possibility of a liquidity trap, the paradox of thrift and toil, a Keynesian-type multiplier, and a rationale for expansionary fiscal policy all emerge naturally from the model. We argue that this approach sheds considerable light both on current economic difficulties and on historical episodes, including Japan&amp;rsquo;s lost decade (now in its 18th year) and the Great Depression itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Was the New Deal Contractionary?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/was-the-new-deal-contractionary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/was-the-new-deal-contractionary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v102y2012i1p524-55.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;eggertsson-2012-was-the-new-deal-contractionary.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Web Appendix&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can government policies that increase the monopoly power of firms and the militancy of unions increase output? This paper shows that the answer is yes under certain &amp;ldquo;emergency&amp;rdquo; conditions. These emergency conditions&amp;ndash;zero interest rates and deflation&amp;ndash;were satisfied during the Great Depression in the United States. The New Deal, which facilitated monopolies and union militancy, was therefore expansionary in the model presented. This conclusion is contrary to a large previous literature. The main reason for this divergence is that this paper incorporates rigid prices and the zero bound on the short-term interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Fiscal Policy Is Effective at Zero Interest Rates?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/what-fiscal-policy-is-effective-at-zero-interest-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/what-fiscal-policy-is-effective-at-zero-interest-rates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;MacroAnnual.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tax cuts can deepen a recession if the short-term nominal interest rate is zero, according to a standard New Keynesian business cycle model. An example of a contractionary tax cut is a reduction in taxes on wages. This tax cut deepens a recession because it increases deflationary pressures. Another example is a cut in capital taxes. This tax cut deepens a recession because it encourages people to save instead of spend at a time when more spending is needed. Fiscal policies aimed directly at stimulating aggregate demand work better. These policies include 1) a temporary increase in government spending; and 2) tax cuts aimed directly at stimulating aggregate demand rather than aggregate supply, such as an investment tax credit or a cut in sales taxes. The results are specific to an environment in which the interest rate is close to zero, as observed in large parts of the world today.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Political Agency Theory of Central Bank Independence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-political-agency-theory-of-central-bank-independence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-political-agency-theory-of-central-bank-independence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/mcb/jmoncb/v42y2010i4p647-677.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;JMCB_EggLeB.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a simple theory to explain why, and under what circumstances, a politician delegates policy tasks to a technocrat in an independent institution and then analyze under what conditions delegation is optimal for society. Our theory builds on Holmstrˆm&amp;rsquo;s (1982, 1999)&amp;ldquo;hidden effort&amp;rdquo; principal-agent model. The election pressures that politicians face, and the absence of such pressures for technocrats, give rise to a dynamic incentive structure that formalizes two rationales for delegation, one highlighted by Hamilton (1788) and the other by Blinder (1998). Delegation trades off the cost of having a possibly incompetent technocrat with a long-term job contract against the benefit of having a technocrat who (i) invests more effort into the specialized policy task and (ii) is better insulated from the whims of public opinion. A natural application of our framework suggests a new theory of central bank independence. Copyright (c) 2010 The Ohio State University.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Expectations and the End of the Depression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/great-expectations-and-the-end-of-the-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/great-expectations-and-the-end-of-the-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v98y2008i4p1476-1516.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Great_Exp_AER.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper suggests that the US recovery from the Great Depression was driven by a shift in expectations. This shift was caused by President Franklin Delano Roosevelt&amp;rsquo;s policy actions. On the monetary policy side, Roosevelt abolished the gold standard and &amp;ndash; even more importantly &amp;ndash; announced the explicit objective of inflating the price level to pre-Depression levels. On the fiscal policy side, Roosevelt expanded real and deficit spending, which made his policy objective credible. These actions violated prevailing policy dogmas and initiated a policy regime change as in Sargent (1983) and Temin and Wigmore (1990). The economic consequences of Roosevelt are evaluated in a dynamic stochastic general equilibrium model with nominal frictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Mistake of 1937: A General Equilibrium Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-mistake-of-1937-a-general-equilibrium-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-mistake-of-1937-a-general-equilibrium-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/ime/imemes/v24ydecemberis1p151-190.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Eggertsson_1108.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper studies a dynamic stochastic general equilibrium model with sticky prices and rational expectations in an environment of low interest rates and deflationary pressures. We show that small changes in the public&amp;rsquo;s beliefs about the future inflation target of the government can lead to large swings in both inflation and output. This effect is much larger at low interest rates than under regular circumstances. This highlights the importance of effective communication policy at zero interest rates. We argue that confusing communications by the U.S. Federal Reserve, the President of the United States, and key administration officials about future price objectives were responsible for the sharp recession in the United States in 1937?38, one of the sharpest recessions in U.S. economic history. Poor communication policy is the mistake of 1937. Before committing the mistake of 1937, the U.S. policymakers faced economic conditions that are similar in some respects to those confronted by Japanese policymakers in the first half of 2006.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Monetary and Fiscal Policy in a Liquidity Trap</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/optimal-monetary-and-fiscal-policy-in-a-liquidity-trap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/optimal-monetary-and-fiscal-policy-in-a-liquidity-trap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/h/nbr/nberch/0076.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;EggertssonWoodford2004.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In previous work (Eggertsson and Woodford, 2003), we characterized the optimal conduct of monetary policy when a real disturbance causes the natural rate of interest to be temporarily negative, so that the zero lower bound on nominal interest rates binds, and showed that commitment to a history-dependent policy rule can greatly increase welfare relative to the outcome under a purely forward-looking inflation target. Here we consider in addition optimal tax policy in response to such a disturbance, to determine the extent to which fiscal policy can help to mitigate the distortions resulting from the zero bound, and to consider whether a history-dependent monetary policy commitment continues to be important when fiscal policy is appropriately adjusted. We find that even in a model where complete tax smoothing would be optimal as long as the zero bound never binds, it is optimal to temporarily adjust tax rates in response to a binding zero bound; but when taxes have only a supply-side effect, the optimal policy requires that the tax rate be raised during the &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, while committing to lower tax rates below their long-run level later. An optimal policy commitment is still history-dependent, in general, but the gains from departing from a strict inflation target are modest in the case that fiscal policy responds to the real disturbance in an appropriate way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Deflation Bias and Committing to Being Irresponsible</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-deflation-bias-and-committing-to-being-irresponsible/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-deflation-bias-and-committing-to-being-irresponsible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/mcb/jmoncb/v38y2006i2p283-321.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;JMCB.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;JMCB-04-086.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper with Appendix&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I model deflation, at zero nominal interest rate, in a microfounded general equilibrium model. I show that one can analyze deflation as a credibility problem if three conditions are satisfied. First: The government&amp;rsquo;s only policy instrument is increasing the money supply by open market operations in short-term bonds. Second: The economy is subject to large negative demand shocks. Third: The government cannot commit to future policy. I call the credibility problem that arises under these conditions the deflation bias. I propose several policies to solve it. They all involve printing money or issuing nominal debt. In addition they require cutting taxes, buying real assets such as stocks, or purchasing foreign exchange. The government &amp;ldquo;credibly commits to being irresponsible&amp;rdquo; by pursuing these policies. It commits to higher money supply in the future so that the private sector expects inflation instead of deflation. This is optimal since it curbs deflation and increases output by lowering the real rate of return.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy Options in a Liquidity Trap</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/policy-options-in-a-liquidity-trap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/policy-options-in-a-liquidity-trap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v94y2004i2p76-79.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;EggertssonWoodfordAER.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No abstract is available for this item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-BibTeX&#34; data-lang=&#34;BibTeX&#34;&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;related-material&#34;&gt;Related material&lt;/h5&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Zero Bound on Interest Rates and Optimal Monetary Policy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-zero-interest-rate-bound-and-optimal-monetary-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-zero-interest-rate-bound-and-optimal-monetary-policy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/bin/bpeajo/v34y2003i2003-1p139-235.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;BrookingsPaper.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper considers the consequences for monetary policy of the zero floor for nominal interest rates. The zero bound can be a significant constraint on the ability of a central bank to combat deflation. The paper shows, in the context of an intertemporal equilibrium model, that open-market operations, even of &amp;ldquo;unconventional&amp;rdquo; types, are ineffective if future policy is expected to be purely forward looking. However, a credible commitment to the right sort of history-dependent policy can largely mitigate the distortions created by the zero bound. In the model, optimal policy involves a commitment to adjust interest rates so as to achieve a time-varying price-level target, when this is consistent with the zero bound. The paper also discusses ways in which other central bank actions, although irrelevant apart from their effects on expectations, may help to make a central bank&amp;rsquo;s commitment to its target more credible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Model of Secular Stagnation: Theory and Quantitative Evaluation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-model-of-secular-stagnation-theory-and-quantitative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/a-model-of-secular-stagnation-theory-and-quantitative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/23093.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;SS.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper formalizes and quantifies the secular stagnation hypothesis, defined as a persistently low or negative natural rate of interest leading to a chronically binding zero lower bound (ZLB).  Output-inflation dynamics and policy prescriptions are fundamentally different from those in the standard New Keynesian framework. Using a 56-period quantitative life cycle model, a standard calibration to US data delivers a natural rate ranging from 1.5% to 2%, implying an elevated risk of ZLB episodes for the foreseeable future. We decompose the contribution of demographic and technological factors to the decline in interest rates since 1970 and quantify changes required to restore higher rates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aging, Output Per Capita and Secular Stagnation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/aging-output-per-capita-and-secular-stagnation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/aging-output-per-capita-and-secular-stagnation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;w24906.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper re-examines the relationship between population aging and economic growth. We confirm previous research such as Cutler, Poterba, Sheiner, and Summers (1990) and Acemoglu and Restrepo (2017) that show positive correlation between measures of population aging and per-capita output growth. Our contribution is demonstrating that this relationship breaks down when the adjustment of interest rates is inhibited by an effective lower bound on nominal rates as took place during the Great Financial Crisis decade. Indeed, during the “secular stagnation regime” of 2008-2015 that prevailed in a number of countries, aging had a negative impact on living standards, consistent with the secular stagnation hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Increased Price Flexibility Stabilizing? Redux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/is-increased-price-flexibility-stabilizing-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/is-increased-price-flexibility-stabilizing-redux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/19886.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;PriceFlex.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the implications of increased price flexibility on output volatility? In a simple
DSGE model, we show analytically that more flexible prices always amplify output volatility
for supply shocks and also amplify output volatility for demand shocks if monetary policy
does not respond strongly to inflation. More flexible prices often reduce welfare, even under
optimal monetary policy if full efficiency cannot be attained. Our results extend to a model
with both sticky information and/or wages. We estimate a quantitative DSGE model using
Bayesian methods and using counterfactual experiments show that our results from the
simple model continue to apply.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sticky prices versus sticky information: Does it matter for policy paradoxes?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/sticky-prices-versus-sticky-information-does-it-matter-for-policy-paradoxes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/sticky-prices-versus-sticky-information-does-it-matter-for-policy-paradoxes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;Eggertsson_Garga_RED_Resub.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper shows that government spending multiplier at the zero lower bound (ZLB) is larger under sticky information than under sticky prices. Similarly, well known paradoxes, e.g., the paradox of toil and the paradox of flexibility become more severe under sticky information. For the case of sticky information it is important to assume that the fiscal policy intervention coincides with the duration of zero interest rates, while such distinction is less important in some special cases for sticky prices. This allows us to unify and clarify results that may appear to contradict each other in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Great Escape? A Quantitative Evaluation of the Fed&#39;s Liquidity Facilities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-great-escape-a-quantitative-evaluation-of-the-feds-liquidity-facilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-great-escape-a-quantitative-evaluation-of-the-feds-liquidity-facilities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v107y2017i3p824-57.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IDEAS&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;AER-DEFK.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce liquidity frictions into an otherwise standard DSGE model with nominal and real rigidities and ask: can a shock to the liquidity of private paper lead to a collapse in short-term nominal interest rates and a recession like the one associated with the 2008 US financial crisis? Once the nominal interest rate reaches the zero bound, what are the effects of interventions in which the government provides liquidity in exchange for illiquid private paper? We find that the effects of the liquidity shock can be large, and show some numerical examples in which the liquidity facilities of the Federal Reserve prevented a repeat of the Great Depression in the period 2008-2009.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rise, Fall, and Resurrection  of Iceland: A Postmortem Analysis  of the 2008 Financial Crisis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-rise-fall-and-resurrection-of-iceland-a-postmortem-analysis-of-the-2008-financial-crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/gauti_website/research/the-rise-fall-and-resurrection-of-iceland-a-postmortem-analysis-of-the-2008-financial-crisis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;benediktsdottirtextfa17bpea.pdf&#34;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper documents how the Icelandic banking system grew from 100 percent of GDP in 1998 to 900 percent of GDP in 2008, when it failed during the global financial crisis. We base our analysis on data from the country’s three largest banks that were made public when the Icelandic parliament lifted, among other things, bank secrecy laws in order to investigate the run-up to the financial crisis. We document how the banks were funded and where the money went, using a comprehensive analysis of their lending. The recovery from the crisis was based on policy decisions that, in hindsight, seem to have worked well. We analyze some of these policies—including emergency legislation, capital controls, alleviation of balance of payments risks, and preservation of financial stability. We also estimate the crisis’s output costs, which were about average when compared with the 147 banking crises documented by Luc Laeven and Fabián Valencia (2012) and the 100 banking crises documented by Carmen Reinhart and Kenneth Rogoff (2014). Our computation of the Icelandic government’s direct costs reveals that its recently concluded negotiations with foreign creditors may even leave it with a net surplus as a consequence of the crisis. However, there is still uncertainty about the ultimate cost, and our benchmark estimate is that the cost was about 5 percent of GDP. We summarize several lessons from the episode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
